[Music]
in this video we're going to tell you a
story filled with courage struggle and
tragedy this is the story of Jon Jones
who entered the Nutty putty cave for a
thrilling adventure but it soon turned
into the most challenging and ultimately
final journey of his life imagine being
trapped in a narrow dark tunnel each
breath growing heavy
each moment shadowed by the fear of
death that's exactly what happened to JN
inside the cave he faced an avalanch of
challenges and his struggle to survive
turned into a living nightmare the cave
was so tight that he couldn't even move
freely rescue teams his family and
friends made every possible effort to
pull Jon out they worked day and night
trying out every method but the narrow
passages and harsh conditions in the
cave made each attempt extremely
difficult called with every effort the
hope of bringing Jon out alive faded bit
by bit and then there came a moment in
John story that would break anyone's
heart so what was that turning point
that made this story a part of History
how did John's Adventure in a cave
turned into a symbol of struggle and
hope and what impact did his dangerous
Journey have on his family and friends
to uncover all this watch the video till
the end because this story has twists
and turns that will leave you speechless
if you enjoy heartfelt and emotional
stories don't forget to subscribe to our
Channel we bring you stories that will
make you think deeply when families
gather for the holidays they usually
plan fun activities to create lasting
memories together the Jones family
decided to explore the Nutty putty caves
unaware of the devastating loss they
were about to face this is the harrowing
account of the Nutty putty cave tragedy
Jon Jones was ready to spend some joyful
time with his family when he decided to
explore the Nutty putty cave located in
Utah's desert near Salt Lake City John
had never been to this particular cave
before though he and his brother Josh
had spent plenty of time exploring
various caves around Utah during their
childhood considering himself an
experienced cave Explorer John said
although my exploring had slowed down
over the last few years I got married
had a child and was currently studying
medicine at the University of Virginia
these commitments kept his schedule
extremely busy leaving little time for
cave exploring over the Thanksgiving
holidays he returned home to relax with
his family and had planned a day of
hiking and exploring at nutty putty a
cave known to most as a beginner's cave
the main sections of the cave held an
Allure for everyone there was a maze
room with multiple paths and tunnels
around large Boulders there was also a
large sloped area called the slide where
the entire room tilt tilted at a 45°
angle with a rope to help descend this
cave system was well mapped in most
explored areas yet some famous sections
remained more challenging like the birth
canal or the aorta crawl these areas
were narrow and hard to pass through so
only the more experienced cavers would
attempt to navigate them despite the
known challenges people would still get
stuck in these tight tunnels nutty putty
had only recently reopened to the public
after after being closed for several
years due to many cavers getting trapped
in these difficult narrow passages for
some these tunnels were navigable but
for others their shoulders or hips
couldn't fit through no matter how hard
they tried once trapped in a narrow area
they would need serious help to be
pulled out because of these rescues a
new permit system had been put in place
requiring each group to have at least
two experienced cavers Josh obtained a
permit for a group exploration on
Tuesday November 24th 2009 for
Thanksgiving John's pregnant wife Emily
stayed home with their one-year-old
daughter Lizzie to enjoy a more relaxed
evening with her in-laws their group of
11 family and friends started in the
main open sections of the cave but
eventually John and his brother Josh
decided to take two friends along to
explore the challenging tunnels they had
heard stories about the birth canal and
consulted the map for its location
this was a long and narrow passage with
an exceptionally tight spot near the end
if they could just make it through the
narrowest part there would be a small
room where they could stand up and turn
around they knew the birth canal would
be tight and potentially disorienting
even for experienced cavers they decided
to spread out on different paths to
locate this particular tunnel John and
Josh chose a small tunnel to the left
advancing about 15 ft this passage wound
about 10 ft with several up and downs in
height there were a few outer Rock
layers and tight spots that required the
caver to contort their body in various
ways it wasn't just a matter of pulling
oneself through with brute strength this
area was known as the cork screw because
those who had passed through were small
and flexible using all their skills to
slowly work their way through its
nerve-wracking twists after the cork
screw area the path turns up about 5 ft
and then sharply to the left into a
rocky crevice at a 90° angle so far
cavers had used this small section as a
turnaround point if needed 5 years
earlier a 16-year-old boy named Brock
Clark had gotten stuck in this very cork
screw section he was only 5' 7 in and
weighed 140 lb yet he got stuck when he
tried to turn it took 14 hours to free
him John was now in the same spot where
Brock had gotten stuck attempting to
turn standing 6 ft tall and weighing 200
lb Jon realized that turning in this
section of the tunnel was simply not an
option for him he found himself in a
space that was only 12 in high where
there wasn't enough room for his pressed
body to turn around he pushed forward
toward the Liz area and squeezed himself
above it it was a tight spot but he felt
there might be an open space below he
pulled his stomach in and moved himself
forward through the narrow passage
pulling himself along the Rocks he was
now moving head first downward but a
turn ahead seemed promising what Jon
didn't know was that no one had ever
passed through this Liz area he was in
completely Uncharted Territory despite
being in such a cramped and
uncomfortable position Jon kept calm he
firmly believed there would be an open
space ahead he thought he was in part of
the birth canal where many cavers had
gotten stuck in the narrow tunnel but
eventually made it out safely as he
crossed through a tight area he began to
slide toward the lower part of this
tunnel he was almost doing a handstand
trying to keep his body steady while
pushing back he still couldn't turn and
now he was upside down gravity was
pulling his 200lb body against the
weakening strength of his hands he
called out to his brother Josh telling
him that he needed to back out they
discussed their options and decided it
was best to move forward and attempt to
turn at this point he was on the verge
of falling onto his shoulders and head
and he had to do something to get out of
this vertical position position his
headlamp gave him a glimpse of a hole in
the floor ahead that might lead to a
larger space feeling a bit more
optimistic he thought about how they
would be laughing about this amazing
experience at Thanksgiving dinner he
made a slight turn and headed toward the
hole it wasn't clear how he ended up in
that tunnel's hole it seemed he had
slipped hit his head and become stuck in
the tight spot another possibility was
that he had peaked into the hole but
misunderstood what he saw thinking it
was an open when it was merely a closed
space in any case Jon found himself in a
small hole at the bottom of the tunnel
impossibly narrow at only 18 in wide and
10 in high slightly larger than a laptop
screen he was almost completely upside
down and wedged at a 70° angle he spent
some time trying to get out of this hole
it was exhausting his hands were trapped
in a useless position one beneath his
chest and the other down on the Rock he
pushed against the walls and soon
realized that all his efforts would not
be enough to pull him back up through
that tight tunnel his calves and legs
were still free in the passage but his
feet were now stuck in the narrowest
part of the hole which was only 8 in
wide he started calling out to Josh
again his voice echoing in the dark
confined space his brother knew that Jon
was trying to turn which didn't bode
well given the precarious situation they
were in Josh made his way back through
the corkscrew route but unlike his
brother he decided to go in feet first
this time he carefully maneuvered his
way forward each movement cautious
knowing the risks involved he continued
to move in the direction of Jon's voice
until he reached above the Liz area he
spotted Jon's foot protruding from the
rock as if it was completely swallowed
by it a sight that sent a wave of
concern through him he slowly Advanced
until his feet caught hold of one of
Jon's legs with a sense of urgency he
tried to p p and lift while Jon pushed
from his side after several feudal
attempts both were exhausted and
frustrated their strength waning as the
minutes ticked by Josh realized the
seriousness of the situation and that
they would need professional help to get
Jon out they agreed that Josh should go
for help while Jon needed to remain as
calm and relaxed as possible during this
challenging time while he went for
assistance one of the other friends from
the family entered the area so that Jon
could know he wasn't alone
offering some comfort in that dark
moment Jon remained stuck upside down
focusing mostly on his breathing each
shallow inhale a reminder of the
tightness around his chest the
constriction made it increasingly
difficult to take anything more than
shallow breaths all his efforts to move
up only pushed him deeper into the
crevice heightening his anxiety over
time gravity continued to pull his
fatigued body against the rough walls of
the tunnel each moment feeling like an
eternity when help arrived the first
caving rescuer Susan Mata reached the
spot where JN was trapped it was now
12:30 a.m. and John had been upside down
for 3 hours the situation becoming
increasingly dire Susan was only 5' 3 in
tall which made it easier for her to
navigate the corkscrew area she had
ropes tied around her ankles so if she
got stuck she would be secured a
precautionary measure that reassured her
she assessed John situation quickly her
professional instincts kicking in and
told him they were going to get him out
it must have brought him some relief to
know that professional help had finally
arrived and that he would soon be free
from this daunting predicament Susan
strapped webbing around his legs and
then sent them down from the beginning
of the tunnel several attempts were made
to pull Jon back up using the ropes but
the friction on the ropes made it
impossible to effectively free him
leaving them frustrated he was
completely stuck without the use of his
hands feeling the weight of his
helplessness after some attempts and
considering several aggressive options
they decided to employ a pulley system
to lift Jon out hoping it would work
where their previous efforts had failed
the pulley had been successfully used 5
years prior when Brock Clark got stuck a
piece of equipment that brought a
glimmer of hope to The Rescuers while
they had a plan to help the space was
not easy to work in with every movement
requiring careful consider itation each
tool had to be brought in from the
entrance which took about an hour to
reach the other side of the cork screw
the tunnel was extremely tight and only
small power tools could be transported
in and out complicating their rescue
efforts only one person could assist at
a time and they had to be small or lean
enough to navigate the passage
effectively it was far from an ideal
situation and time was running out every
pulley installation was taking an
extraordinary amount of time during this
the cave Rescuers were trying to engage
JN in conversation comforting him and
sharing stories to keep him calm and
talking he was a devoted Mormon singing
and praying to find peace in this
unbelievable situation John had spent
the night upside down and his body was
showing signs of the physical limits of
staying in this position the human body
is not designed to remain upside down
for extended periods the entire
circulatory system is designed to move
blood forward by the beating of the
heart while valves and tendons prevent
blood from pooling or flowing backward
it balances the one-way flow of fluid
gravity and valves to ensure oxygen is
available to all tissues and the toxins
are removed from the body through the
kidneys Jon's body had been fighting
against gravity for over 12 hours the
brain is not built to endure this kind
of fluid pressure fluid was accumulating
in his lungs and talk toxins were
building up due to a lack of proper
circulation his organs were pressing
against his lungs making each breath an
exhausting effort as his muscles weren't
made for such tasks his breaths were
slowing and he was completely fatigued
from the effort throughout the night he
had shifted from being completely calm
and clear-headed to helplessly flailing
his legs and hallucinating it was
heartbreaking for The Rescuers to
witness they felt helpless exhausted and
trapped themselves the air in the cave
system was hot and humid when you're
limited and can't breathe properly
taking a peaceful breath Demands a
concerted effort but The Rescuers knew
that when necessary they could
eventually get out John didn't have that
luxury he couldn't expand his chest to
breathe and the air around him was
gradually losing its oxygen
concentration meanwhile a wireless
Telecom system was brought to the
location where Jon was trapped
his wife spoke to him encouraging him to
be patient and keep the faith John
assured her that he would soon be with
her by then it was 4:00 a.m. and they
had finally succeeded in placing the
pulleys to lift him Ryan shirtz was in
the tunnel when the system was prepared
for testing Jon's body was stuck in the
narrow section of the crevice so Ryan
had to push his legs upward while the
team pulled from outside with every pull
he was hoisted inch by inch by this time
John was experiencing unbearable pain in
his legs the Rope had been tied around
his feet for hours as The Rescuers tried
various methods to get him out his legs
had turned completely blue and there was
no discernable pulse still with every
pull he asked them to stop as his nerves
had become extremely sensitive they gave
him a moment to collect himself and then
tried again it seemed to be working Jon
was finally being pulled out of the hole
he was raised high enough for Ryan to
approach his leg
and pass him a tube to drink some
Gatorade this attempt was excruciatingly
slow and everyone could feel the fatigue
from this grueling effort Ryan was
wedged in the 12-in high tunnel with his
neck close to Jon's legs as they slowly
tried to extract him from the tight
10-in fissure although they were making
some progress in lifting him they were
still far from getting him out
completely Jon's feet were hitting the
upper ceiling of the tunnel making it
impossible to maneuver them in that
space he had no control over his legs at
this point after spending 19 hours
upside down John's knees were being
gently bent without his help they
seriously considered breaking his legs
to bring him back into the tunnel as
time was quickly running out for John
Suddenly a sharp pain hit Ryan and he
fainted when he came to he was bleeding
profusely and feeling incredibly
disoriented the rope that anchored the
pulley to the Cave's natural Arch had
snapped sending the Carabiner and pulley
crashing directly into Ryan's face he
sustained injuries to his face lips and
tongue as well as a concussion he needed
to get out of there quickly Jon found
himself back in the same spot completely
stuck in the tunnel his arms devoid of
blood circulation and his legs were
completely numb he was unable to free
himself in any way this moment marked
the beginning of Jon Jones's ultimate
defeat while Ryan was checked in the pit
and then sent to the hospital his father
Dave came to take Ryan's place in the
tunnel with John it took an hour to
reestablish the pulley lines and Dave
struggled to wrap a rope around Jon's
body but he couldn't manage to get the
Rope around Jon's trapped torso for the
entire time that Dave was with JN he was
unresponsive throughout this whole
ordeal Jon needed assistance for an
effective rescue lifting his 200 lb 6-t
frame without his help was simply
impossible during Dave's attempts to buy
IND John he too found himself stuck for
about 15 minutes this serious effort to
save Jon's life put both him and his son
at risk this was a devastating reality
as he pushed himself into the 12-in
tunnel he grew exhausted and needed to
get out of there Brandon coils took his
place and brought a telecom system to
connect with Jon's family his wife Emily
expressed her love and told him to rest
for a while after all their efforts he
genuinely believed he would make it out
but Brandon could see what she could not
Jon was no longer responding and there
had been no signs of life from him in
the past few hours Ryan reported that
Jon had been breathing in a wheezing
manner but now there was silence the
rescue team gathered in the pit area of
the cave to discuss the situation it was
decided that a medical professional
would be sent in to confirm whether he
had truly passed away a paramedic was
sent into the tight space to make this
confirmation on Wednesday no nober 25th
at 11:56 a.m. Jon Jones was declared
dead the rescue teams had worked
tirelessly for 24 hours trying to free
Jon but his inverted position made it
impossible the Clock Was ticking and
Jon's time had run out John had spent an
extraordinary 27 hours in an inverted
position three times longer than
estimated the six Rescuers who actually
reached Jon were true heroes they placed
themselves in a part of the cave that
was not on the map and faced many known
dangers they demonstrated selflessness
in their efforts maintained a calm
demeanor and never gave up on what
seemed like an impossible rescue when it
was determined that recovering the body
would be impossible Jon was left in the
Nutty putty Cave's AIDS push section for
Eternal rest the entire cave system was
sealed with concrete to prevent any
further exploration a plaque was erected
there in memory of Jon Jones life